Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim.
And we see this beautiful picture here
of a mother with her baby.
Here's the real story!
Don't forget we're telling this story
of the nun named Blue
Lotus or Indigo Lotus
because Pabongka Rinpoche
wants to illustrate that,
as we go through life, things change,
our relationships change,
we never know what was going
on before or after this life.
That's the theme behind this story.
We went to The Sutra of
the Wise and the Foolish
and we found this story and
we're telling the whole story.
Which is why this Lam Rim
is taking so many years.
BDAG KYANG KUN TU RGYU
BA'I RIGS SU SKYES TE
I was born into a KUN TU RGYU BA'I RIGS
This is a kind of a
religious Brahmin family
called Wanderers.
They're not like Brahmins,
but they are a respectable,
religious Hindu family
I was born into.
KHO MO'I.
By the way, Tim, means me, as a woman.
KHO MO'I PHA MA YANG RIGS CHE
My parents were of a high caste and
BTZUN PAS
they were also very religious.
KHO MO YANG KUN TU RGYU RIGS CHE BA
They found for me
another person of the
same caste as a husband.
MANG DU THOS PA
He was very learned.
RIGS BYED DANG LDAN PA ZHEG
He knew the Vedas.
He was a Veda master, which
is a very desirable husband.
ZHEG LA BAG MAR BTANG
They married me off to him
NAS DE'I CHUNG MA BYED DE
and I became his wife.
CHUNG MA means little one, little lady
and it can mean wife,
but it can also mean younger wife
if the other person had two wives.
DE'I BU YANG YOD PAR GYUR TO
And we had a child together.
PHYIS GYOS RGYUG TSE 'PHOS
PA'I 'OG TU KHO MO LA
SEMS CAN YOD PAR GYUR
Later on, my mother-in-law passed away,
and I became SEMS CAN YOD PA
For a hundred dollars, Tim.
Oh I hope, you can probably
see it in the notes.
SEMS CAN YOD PA
It took me about 10
minutes to figure it out.
SEMS CAN YOD
Think of the context. She got married.
- [Tim] (indistinct)
- Nah, forget it. She got pregnant.
(laughter)
- [Tim] Oh, I see.
- She got living-being-haver.
It's cute. I finally said, Oh yeah, okay.
SEMS CAN YOD PAR GYUR NAS
She got pregnant and
KHYIM THAB
she had servants in the
house, helpers in the house.
LA, 'DI SKAD CES BYAS SO
And I said to the other servant,
to the servants in the house
KHO MO LA SEMS CAN YOD
I have a SEMS CAN
I'm pregnant.
ZLA BA YANG TSANG
And the month are now full,
meaning nine months have passed,
or close to nine months.
DU NYE BAS
The time is near.
GAL TE 'DIR BU BTZAS NA
If I give birth to my
child here in this house,
BTZOG PO
it's a little bit not so clean here and
MI BTUB
it's not that convenient. So I'm thinking,
KHO MO'I PHA MA'I KHYIM DU BTZAR 'GRO'O
I'm going to go have my
child at my parents' home.
KHO MO LA LEGS SO
My house servants told
me that's a good idea.
ZHES ZER TE, KHYO SHUG GNYIS 'GROGS NAS
So two married couples of
servants accompanied me.
BU ZHIG KYANG KHRID DE
I took a child with me and
PHA MA 'DOD PAR SONG BA LAS
and I went to where my parents lived.
I went to go to my parents.
LAM PHYED TZAM DU PHYIN PA
Halfway to their house, along the road
MNGAL MI BDE BAR GYUR
I felt something uncomfortable in my womb.
SHING ZHIG GI DRUNG DU
We stopped at the base of a tree.
NAM PHYED TZAM NA
Around midnight,
BU BTZAS SO
my child was born. My son was born.
KHO MO'I KHYIM THAB KYANG LOGS SHIG
So now she has two boys with her
and the two couples.
KHO MO'I KHYIM THAB KYANG
LOGS SHIG NA NYAL BA
One of the couples set up camp nearby
where I was having my baby.
MTSAN MO SBRUL GYIS ZIN TO
And they were attacked
by a snake in the night.
MTSAN MO BOS NA CANG MI GRAG NAS
They tried to call out
but no one heard them.
NAM LANGS TE
And then the sun came up the next morning.
BLTAS NA
And I looked at their campsite.
KHYIM THAB KYANG SBRUL
GDUG PAS ZIN PAS TSE 'PHOS
I saw that the snake had killed them,
poisoned them with poison,
LUS KYANG ZHIG PAR GYUR TO
and eaten their bodies mostly.
DE'I TSE NA KHO MO 'KHAMS TE
I passed out from the
shock and I fell down.
SA LA 'GYEL BA
And I ended up on the ground.
BU CHE BA YANG PHA SBRUL GYIS BSAD PA
Then the older son,
that was already there,
his father died also, was
killed by another snake.
MTHONG NAS SKAD PHYUNG STE NGUS PAS
I cried out in suffering and weeping.
BU NGUS PA'I SKAD GYIS
KHO MO YANG PHYIR SANGS
Sorry, The boy started
crying and that woke me up.
When he saw his father dead,
he was crying and that woke me up.
And this larger child ...
So now I have two kids:
I have one previous son
who walked into the jungle with us
to go to my parents' house
so I could have the other child,
but the other child was
born suddenly at night.
So I put the older kid on my back.
KHUR DU THOGS
There's KHUR again, a load on the back.
BU CHUNG BA NI
By the way, that sutra
was especially difficult
because in this one sentence,
there are one, two, three, four,
five, six spelling mistakes.
THOGS BU CHUNG BA PHANG BAR KHYER TE
I put the younger, the
new child, on my hip.
And weeping as I went,
SONG SONG SONG
I walked, and walked, and walked.
LAM YANG DBEN PA ZHIG STE
Then I got to a
sort of a wild part of the forest,
desolate part of the forest.
YANG MI 'DRUL
I couldn't find anyone to help me.
There was no other person on the road
and it was passing to a deserted area.
MA RNYED DO
There's RNYED that we had
to find or to locate.
BAR NA CHU CHEN PO
BAR NA here means there
came a time in the interim,
somewhere along the road,
CHU CHEN PO ZHIG YOD DE
we came to a great river.
CHU'I KHA TSO NA , misspelled.
YANG CHE LA ZAB PAS
The river was very wide and very deep.
BU GNYI GA MA THEG NAS
Here's THEG PA as 'yana',
meaning, I didn't have
the vehicular capacity
to carry both kids.
So there's a great ancient
use of the word THEG,
meaning to be able to carry.
GNYI GA MA THEG
I couldn't carry both
kids across the river. So,
BU CHE BA NI CHU'I
misspelled,
CHU {%TSU) ROL DU BZHAG
extremely difficult misspelling.
I left the one, the older
boy, on the near shore.
And then I took the
younger boy, the newborn,
BU CHUNG NGU KHYER TE
I carried him
PHA ROL TU BSKYAL
and I forded across to the
other side of the river.
BSKYAL NAS PHYIR CHE BA BSUR 'ONGS PA DANG
And then I turned back.
This PHYIR means turned back and the
CHE BA BSUR 'ONGS PA DANG means
I went back to get the older boy
on the near side, who I had left
while I would carry the
newborn to the other side.
She sat the newborn on
the ground and came back.
BU YANG MA 'ONG
And here it's confusing, because this MA
is not MA 'ONG, it's
MA
'ONG
The older boy saw his mother coming.
CHU'I NANG DU ZHUGS
So he stepped into the river.
ZHUGS TE CHUS KHYER
and he was carried away by the current.
KHO MOS BSNYAGS NA
And I reached out for him.
STOBS CHUNG BSAM  MA ZIN
Misspelled.
But I didn't have the
power to hold on to him.
I got his arm, but I couldn't keep it on,
I couldn't hold on to it.
And the river carried him away.
DE NAS PHYIR PHA ROL TU PHYIN
Here's PHA ROL TU PHYIN PA in the
ancient form to go to the other side.
PHYIR means I went back.
So I turned around and I went back
to the far side of the river.
BU CHUNG NGU YANG
SPYANG KIS means a coyote or a wolf.
ZOS
Past tense. Ate.
And I realized the newborn had been eaten
by a wolf on the other side of the river.
KHRAG CUNG ZAD TZAM SA LA SNANG NGO
And he was reduced to a
stain of blood in the soil,
a small puddle of blood in the soil.
That's all that was left.
DER YANG 'KHAMS NAS
Misspelled.
I started to wander around in grief.
RING ZHIG LON TE
After many, many hours and a few days
SANGS PA
Here is the SANGS in SANGS RGYAS
which means to become aware.
So I came back to my senses.
These are ancient, ancient, useful words.
SANGS PA DANG LAM DU ZHUGS TE
I got back on the road
to my parents' house.
SONG SONG SONG
I walked, and walked, and walked.
KUN TU RGYU KHO MO'I PHA MA DANG NYE ZHING
BSHES PA ZHIG
Then I ran into a member
of the same caste,
who was a friend of my parents.
The Wandering caste.
PHRAD NAS KUN TU RGYU DES KHYOD CI NYES NA
'DI LTAR NYON MONGS PAR GYUR CES DRIS NA
What's wrong with you?
And why have you gotten
so NYON MONGS PAed?
What's distressing you?
There's the ancient meaning of NYON MONGS.
What's distressing you so badly?
KHO MOS KYANG JI LTAR GYUR
PA RGYAS PAR GTAM BYAS
So I told him the whole story extensively.
GTAM means to tell a story,
told him the whole story.
KUN TU RGYU DE YANG DUS (%NGUS)
Misspelled.
He started to weep also and
KHO MOS PHA MA'I GTAM DRIS NA
And then I said, 'How
are my parents doing?'
And he said,
'KHYOD KYI PHA MA'I KHYM DU DE BAR ME SHOR
Your parents' house caught on fire
since the last time you heard from them.
PHA MA DANG KHYIM GANG GI MI THAMS CAD
Your mother, your father, and everybody
in the house was burned to death.
MES TSIG GO, ZHES ZER RO
He told me.
DE SKAD CES SMRAS PA
THOS NAS KHO MO 'KHAMS TE
When I heard what happened to my parents,
I passed out again and fell to the earth.
SA LA 'GYEL TO
means I fell to the earth unconscious.
DE NAS KUN TU RGYU DES BLSAD  STE
Misspelled.
Then that person from my
same caste picked me up,
KHYIM DU KHRID NAS
and led me to my parents' house.
KHO MO LA BU BZHIN
sorry, to his house,
and treated me like their own child.
That family took me in and
treated me like their own kin.
SHING 'DUG PA
And I started living there with them.
YANG KUN TU RGYU GCIG CHUNG MAR BLANGS TE
And in time, another man approached me
and we got close, and
I was married to him.
BLANGS TE DE DANG LHAN CIG
RTZE DGA' YONGS SU SPYOD PA
We enjoyed love and pleasure,
meaning they had sex.
And SEMS CAN, I became
SEMS CAN LDAN
I became living being-ed again.
ZLA BA TSANG NAS
When the months were
complete, nine months, right?
BU 'BYUNG DU
I had a child. A child came out.
Sorry, when the child
was close to coming out,
'BYUNG DU NYE BA NA KHYIM THAB
GZHAN GYI KHYIM DU TSANG LA
BOS NAS
I decided I would need some help,
so I went to another family's house.
DE'I 'OG TU BDAG BU BTZAS TE
And I gave birth on the
floor of their house.
SGO DAM DU BCAD
I had made the door fast
after I got to their house
because I guess there
was nobody at the house.
So I went inside,
I shut the doors,
and, I don't know, bolted it?
And then I laid down and had the baby.
SGO DAM DU BCAD PHU 'TSIR
There's the word for squeezing sponsors
I squeezed out the baby.
KHYIM THAB CHANG GIS MYOS TE
And the owner of the house
came back totally drunk.
Apparently he's a bad guy.
He came back to the house totally drunk.
MYOS TE SGO BRDUNGS
He banged on the door. I
couldn't get up to open it.
So he
SGO 'BYED PA MED PAS
Because he couldn't open the door
KHROS TE
he got pissed off and
SGO BCAG
he smashed the door down,
NANG DU 'ONGS
came inside and also beat me.
Gave me a good beating.
I just had given birth to a child.
BDAG GIS BU BTZAS SO
I said, 'Look, I just
gave birth to a child.'
BU YANG BSAD DE
He killed the child and
fried it in a frying pan.
He took the child's body and
BRDOS NAS KHO MO KHO YANG ZAR BCUG
And he tried to get me to
eat the child's flesh also.
BU'I SHA ZA MA PHOD
I couldn't do it.
DE MA ZOS PAS YANG BRDEGS
And because I wouldn't
eat the child's flesh,
he beat me up again.
NAN GYIS ZAR BCUG
And then he forced the food into my mouth,
forced my own child's flesh into my mouth.
ZOS PA'I 'OG TU KHYIM THAB KYANG SANGS
Then after I had eaten my child,
I came back to my senses.
BDAG GIS BSAM PA
And I thought to myself,
BDAG BSOD NAMS MED
I don't have any
BSOD NAMS
Apparently I don't have
any good karma at all.
MED CING LAS NGAN NO
My karma is all bad.
SNYAM NAS KHYIM THAB BOR TE
I decided to give up the home life
and I headed for Varanasi.
WA RA n'A SIR BROS SO
I escaped to Varanasi.
YUL WA RA n'A SA'I PHYI ROL
NA SHING ZHIG GI DRUNG NA
'DUG PA LAS
Outside of Varanasi city,
I was sitting at the base of a tree.
GRONG DE'I KHYIM THAB GZHON NU ZHIG GSAR
There was a young family man
of the city who had come out of the city
to bury his wife's ashes.
His wife had died.
CHUNG MA TSE 'PHOS means
'PHOS BAR, right?
His own wive had died and
GRONG KHYER DE'I PHYI ROL DU
outside of the city,
CHUNG MA'I RUS BU SBAS NAS
he was burying or hiding the
bones of his cremated wife.
KHYIM BDAG DE CHUNG MA
DE LA CHAGS PAS, RUS PU
He had been very close to his wife.
RUS PU'I DUNG NA
Again, everything misspelled.
DU  ZHING 'DUG PA LAS
He was sitting at her graveside crying
and I came upon him.
BDAG GI DRUNG DU 'ONGS TE KHO
MO LA KHYOD GCIG PU 'DI NA
CI BYED CES DRIS SO
And he saw me and he said,
'What are you doing here by yourself?'
Like an Indian woman never is outside
by herself in the forest.
He said, 'What are you
doing here by yourself?'
KHO MOS KYANG DE BZHIN DU GTAM BYAS PA LAS
I told him my whole story.
KHYIM BDAG DES SKYED MOS TSAL DU KHRID DE
He took me to the Jetavan.
Jetavana.
The garden, the garden.
Sorry, this is not the Jetavana.
This is just a general royal park.
He took me to the royal park,
which is where Buddha hangs out usually.
KHRID DE KHO MO LA CHUNG
MA BYA'O, ,ZHES SMRAS NAS
He said, 'Hey, how about we get married
and you become my wife?'
KHO MO KYANG DE BZHIN DU RUNG NGO
I said, 'Well, that would be
okay. I don't have a husband.'
KHYO SHUG TU 'DUS NAS
We became man and wife.
RING PO MA LON PAR
After not long,
KHYIM BDAG
my husband,
NAD KYIS BTAB
stricken by disease,
TSE 'PHOS
He died.
DE'I TSE NA YUL CHOS KYIS
GSON PA'I TSE KHYO SHUG
MDZA' BA RNAMS KHYO TSE 'PHOS NA
And according to the current
customs of that part of India,
if the husband died and
the wife was still alive,
MDZA RNAMS KHYO TSE 'PHOS
NA, CHUNG MA YANG GSON POR
KHYO DANG LHAN CIG TU DUR DU 'JUG GO
What's is DUR KHROD?
Remember? In Vajrayana,
it's a burial ground.
According to the custom
of that part of India,
the wife should be buried
alive with the husband's body,
which still happens.
KHO MO YANG DE LTAR DUR DU BCUG NAS
So they buried me with him.
But after sunset, some grave robbers came
to dig and try to see if there's
any jewelry on the bodies.
'ONGS TE DUR BRUS
They dug down into where I was and
DUR RKUN GYI DPON POS KHO MO BZANG BAR
The chief of the robber
band saw that I was alive.
BZANG BA
Still hale and healthy.
MTHONG BAS, DES KYANG CHUNG MAR
I became his CHUNG MAR.
He took me as his wife.
I don't know how many times now.
RING PO MA LON PAR
Before long had passed,
BRKUR SONG BA LAS
on a robbing trip,
RGYAL POS BSAD
the king killed him.
He was killed by the king's
troops on a robbing trip.
RKUN ZLA RNAMS KYIS RUS
BU BKUR TE KHO MO DANG
LHAN CIG YANG DUR DU BCUG GO
So his companions took his bones
and buried me with them again.
I was buried again with the
corpse of my next husband.
DUR NA ZHANG GSUM 'DUG 'DUG PA LAS
I was three full days half-buried
in the burial ground and a
SPYANG KIS
another wolf came to dig me out.
I guess he didn't ask her to be his wife.
KHO MO YANG DUR NAS BYUNG STE
And then by accident, he dug
me out of the grave as well.
And I started to think about it.
'DI SNYAM DU BSAMS SO
I started thinking to myself.
KHO MOS SNGON SDIG PA CIG GI BYAS NA
Misspelled.
What did I do in my past life
that was so bad that this
keeps happening to me?
'DI 'DRA BAR LAN DU MA SHI
BA LAS PHYIR SOS PAR GYUR
And why do I keep getting
saved at the last minute?
Why do I keep surviving?
SNGON THOS NA
In a previous life,
SH'AKYA'I RIGS KYI SRAS SHIG
MNGON PAR BYANG CHUB NAS
it appears that a certain
prince of the Shakya clan
had become enlightened,
sorry, in this life.
MTSAN YANG
And they started calling him, Buddha.
SANGS RGYAS
Some Shakya prince got enlightened
and people started calling him Buddha.
'DAS PA DANG, MA 'ONGS PA
KUN MKHYEN NO, ZHES GRAG NA
It's supposed to be that
he can see all things
of past and future.
So maybe he can tell me
what the hell is going on.
I'll go find him and ask him,
'What did I do that this
is all happening to me?'
DA NI, DE LA SKYAMS SU
'GRO'O SNYAM BSAMS NAS
I thought, 'Let me go
and seek his shelter.'
SKYABS 'GRO
This is literal meaning of SKYABS 'GRO
Going for refuge.
RGYAL BU RGYAL BYED KYI TSAL
Then she went to the Jetavana,
which is Shravasti.
She went outside the city of Shravasti
to the gardens of Prince Jeta
TSAL GANG NA BA DE LOGS SU SONG BA
I went to that place
RGYANG MA NAS
and from a distance,
DE BZHIN GSHEGS PA ME TOG
GI SDONG PO RGYAS PA LTA BU
I saw Lord Buddha, who looked like,
from a distance, he looked
like a huge flower opening.
SKAR MA'I NGANG NA ZLA
BA LTA BUR MTHONG NGO
Or you can say he looked
like the full moon
surrounded by the stars of the galaxy.
Very beautiful. From a
distance, he looked like that.
DE'I TSE BCOM LDAN 'DAS
KYIS KYANG THOGS PA
MED PA'I YE SHE KYIS
At that moment, the
Buddha was also employing
his unstoppable
THOGS MED
Asanga -- wisdom.
BDAG GDUL BA'I DUS LA BAB PAR MKHYEN
He saw that the time had come.
DUS LA BAB
The time had befallen that
I should be GDUL BAed.
That I should become a disciple.
MKHYEN NAS BZHENGS
Honorific, he rose from his seat and
KHO MO BSU'O
he greeted me.
Very beautiful. This
scene is very beautiful.
I was buck naked
because I just got out of the grave.
I was completely naked.
NGO TSA
Out of NGO TSA
out of shame,
with my hand, I covered my breasts.
BKAB NAS
I covered my breasts
and I just sat where I
was because I was afraid
to stand and approach him.
And bad news!
We're going to to stop the story there
because you will have to
come back to find out
the rest of the story.
So this is like those TV shows where
you have to come back for
the rest of the story.
- [Woman] Like a good book.
- Yeah, like a good book.
So that happens to be
where we should split the story
and we'll pick it up in the next class.
But don't forget, why we're
talking about this story
is that from lifetime to lifetime,
here's a nun who became an arhat
at the feet of Lord Buddha himself.
She was trained by the
first nun of all, Prajapati.
So we're talking about
you never know who somebody is.
Right now, she's a naked, crazy woman
who just crawled out of a grave.
What's going to happen?
Find out next time. See you then.